Oversight Panel for the Task Force on Race Records UA123
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Oversight Panel for the Task Force on Race Records
1996 -- 2004
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Task Force on Race
UA123
1.7 Linear Feet 2 boxes
This collection contains material likely compiled by the Tufts University Oversight Panel for the Task on Race co-chair Anne Gardulski between 1996 and 2005. The Task Force on Race was created in 1996 by the President and Vice President for Arts, Sciences, and Technology to investigate race relations on campus. The Oversight Panel was created by the Task Force on Race in 1998 to monitor the progress of the recommendations created for campus by the Task Force. Materials include administrative files, publications, reports, and demographic research.
Arrangement
This collection consists of one series: Oversight Panel for the Task Force on Race Records.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials documenting people and events related to the Oversight Panel for the Task Force on Race and the Task Force on Race at Tufts University from 1996-2005. The records appear to have been created and compiled by Anne Gardulski, professor of geology at Tufts University and co-chair of the Oversight Panel for the Task Force on Race. The collection includes reports, articles, administrative files, newspaper clippings, publications, meeting notes, communications, and questionnaires. Other materials include incident reports, demographic information, departmental hiring plans, and student applications for membership on the panel.
Biographical / Historical
The Task Force on Race was commissioned by the University in 1996 to create recommendations that would proactively increase awareness of the value of diversity; identify problematic policies and practices that marginalized students of color; and develop ways to counteract that marginalization. The Task Force created recommendations for most departments on campus, and then created an Oversight Panel to monitor the enactment of those recommendation. The Task Force was led by two co-chairs, Anne Gardulski and Michael Powell. There were also a number of faculty, student, and administrative members (listed in detail below). The Task Force was broken down into three subgroups under the following categories: Institutional Policy, Academic Experience, and Campus Life. Each subgroup developed recommendations related specifically to their assigned topics and included those recommendations in the final report.
Members of the Task Force included: President John DiBaggio and Vice President Mel Bernstein; Co-Chairs Anne Gardulski and Michael Powell; Center directors Ruben Salinas Stern, Linell Yugawa, and Todd McFadden; Faculty members Mei Ho, Fred Nelson, Andrew McClellan, Kathleen Weiler, Gerald Gill, and Jonathan Strong; Student members Emily Adler, Aliguma Kabadaki, Ryan Centner, Ashish Shah, Hillary Bassett, and Kim Nguyen; Ex Officio Leila Fawaz, Ioannis Miaoulis, Walt Swap, Marilyn Glater, Jean Wu, Rommel Childress, and Bobbie Knable; and Senate Representative Amdo Freedman. Members served for three semesters from the Fall of 1996 through the Fall of 1997.
In 1998 the Oversight Panel was established to track the progress of the original recommendations and assist the departments with any issues they may have while completing the recommendations. The Panel instituted student and faculty forums to discuss issues of race on campus, and from 1999-2003 released multiple reports on the progress of the Task Force recommendations. After releasing the final report in 2003 the Oversight Panel remained active in monitoring issues of race on campus for a number of years. The Oversight Panel consisted of eight positions, held by both new and former members of the Task Force. Members of the oversight panel included: Anne Gardulski, Jeff Berry, Lin Brown, Francie Chew, Badi Foster; ex officio Lisette Garcia and Michaele Whelan; Student members Sean Hassan, Mernaysa Rivera, and Margery Yeager.
Conditions Governing Access
University records are closed for 20 years from the date of their creation. Records older than 20 years that do not pertain to student education, staff and faculty employment and Board of Trustees records are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by the office of the Task Force on Race, 2006, accession number 2007.001.
Administration and Governance -- Planning, evaluation, policies & procedures; Student life; Employment and Human Resources
- Oversight Panel for the Task Force on Race Records, 1996 -- 2004; UA123.000002; Task Force on Race; DiBiaggio, John A.; Bernstein, Melvin; 2.4 Linear Feet 2 boxes
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains materials documenting people and events related to the Oversight Panel for the Task Force on Race at Tufts University from 1996-2005. The records appear to have been created and compiled by Anne Gardulski, professor of geology at Tufts University and co-chair of the Oversight Panel for the Task Force on Race. The collection includes reports, articles, administrative files, newspaper clippings, publications, meeting notes, emails, memos, and questionnaires. Other materials include incident reports, demographic information, departmental hiring plans, and student applications for membership on the panel.
  Administration and Governance -- Planning, evaluation, policies & procedures; Student life; Employment and Human Resources
  - Task Force - personnel, circa 1996; UA123.000006; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Open for research.
  - AD HOC reports, circa 1996; UA123.000007; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Task Force: subgroups, circa 1996; UA123.000008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - AD HOC reports and policies, circa 1996; UA123.000009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Diversity workshop, 1997-01-13 -- 1997-01-14; UA123.000010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Communications on first year experience, 1997-02; UA123.000011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Task Force on Race - interim report, 1997-04-11; UA123.000012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Springfield: A commUNITY in Progress report, 1997-09-10; UA123.000013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Campus-life sub-committee report, 1997-10; UA123.000014; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Final report - Task Force on Race, 1997-12-05; UA123.000015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - TFOR report - final report, 1997-12-05; UA123.000016; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Final report - Task Force on Race, 1997-12-05; UA123.000017; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Final - report, 1997-12-05; UA123.000018; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Task Force memos, 1997-12-10; UA123.000019; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Task Force correspondence and reference materials, 1997-04; UA123.000020; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - National Conference on the Advancement of Student Diversity program and Task Force communications, circa 1997; UA123.000021; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Task Force "Academic Experience Report" papers, circa 1997; UA123.000022; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Advising handbook and related papers, circa 1997; UA123.000023; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Academic experience, circa 1997; UA123.000024; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Task Force on Race meeting agenda, notes, and background materials, circa 1997; UA123.000025; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Institutional policy, circa 1997; UA123.000026; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Task Force: recommendation report, circa 1997; UA123.000027; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Task Force - race meetings, circa 1997; UA123.000028; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Task force meeting notes, circa 1997; UA123.000029; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Significant Differences in Responses by Race report and the Peard Bay #1 files, circa 1997; UA123.000030; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Task Force faculty papers, circa 1997; UA123.000031; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Racial demographics, circa 1997; UA123.000032; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - MAP meeting - racial demographics, circa 1997 -- 2003; UA123.000033; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 4)
    20 years from date of creation.
  - Task Force report notes, circa 1997; UA123.000034; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Task Force forums, circa 1997; UA123.000035; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Task Force reports and meeting materials, circa 1997; UA123.000036; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Task Force meeting materials, circa 1997; UA123.000037; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Summary assessment of implementation of recommendations of the Task Force on Race, circa 1997 -- 2003; UA123.000038; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Task Force reference materials, circa 1997; UA123.000039; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Task Force reports, circa 1997; UA123.000040; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Task Force - interested students, circa 1997; UA123.000041; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Task Force - phone calls, circa 1997; UA123.000042; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Task Force - articles, etc., circa 1997; UA123.000043; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Priority recommendations report, circa 1997 -- 2003; UA123.000044; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Task Force - misc. info., circa 1998; UA123.000045; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Task Force communications, circa 1998; UA123.000046; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Rapid response team info, circa 1998; UA123.000047; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Panel meetings, circa 1998 -- 1999; UA123.000048; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Responsible office prelim and recommendation communication, circa 1998 -- 1999; UA123.000049; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Meeting materials, 1999-01-25; UA123.000050; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Oversight Committee forum and papers, 1999-04-22; UA123.000051; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Report, 1999-05-14; UA123.000052; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Misc. info - reference materials, circa 1999; UA123.000053; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Tufts Publications, circa 1999; UA123.000054; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence - Oversight Panel, circa 1999; UA123.000055; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Oversight Panel - work in progress, circa 1999; UA123.000056; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Response request, 1999; UA123.000057; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Responses, 1999; UA123.000058; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Report and appendices, 1999 -- 2000; UA123.000059; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Info - misc. Task Force and Oversight Panel, 1999 -- 2000; UA123.000060; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Responses - originals and Oversight Panel questionnaire, 1999 -- 2000; UA123.000061; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Copies of Oversight Panel reports, circa 1999; UA123.000062; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Applicants, circa 1999; UA123.000063; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Higher education initiative, circa 1999; UA123.000064; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Diversity info/discussion sessions, circa 1999; UA123.000065; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Forum recommendations, 2000-04-25; UA123.000066; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Grad student project, 2000; UA123.000067; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Copies of responses and Oversight Panel questionnaire, 2000; UA123.000068; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Priority recommendations reports, circa 2000; UA123.000069; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Confronting intolerance, circa 2000; UA123.000070; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Oversight Panel reports, circa 2000; UA123.000071; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Task Force data and info, circa 2000; UA123.000072; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Reported incidents of bias - Tufts Daily, 2002; UA123.000073; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Oversight Panel - general, circa 2003; UA123.000074; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Oversight Panel papers, circa 2003; UA123.000075; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Oversight Panel drafts, circa 2003; UA123.000076; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Oversight Panel materials, 2003 -- 2004; UA123.000077; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Oversight Panel materials, 2004 -- 2005; UA123.000078; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 49)